<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Monthly Updates | MFR</title>
    <link>https://mragsac.github.io/categories/monthly-updates/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mragsac.github.io/categories/monthly-updates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Monthly Updates</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Michelle Franc Ragsac © 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 15:09:03 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mragsac.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Monthly Updates</title>
      <link>https://mragsac.github.io/categories/monthly-updates/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Madness 2020</title>
      <link>https://mragsac.github.io/2020/04/09/spring-madness-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 15:09:03 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mragsac.github.io/2020/04/09/spring-madness-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since my last update, it feels like the world has turned upside down for everybody. I hope that people are doing okay amid all of the coronavirus craziness! In California, we&amp;rsquo;ve been sheltering in place for the past three-ish weeks now, and it seems like the panic is settling a little bit where I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve been up to since my last update—it&amp;rsquo;s not everything, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a little on the longer side!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jumping-back-into-science-outreach&#34;&gt;Jumping Back into Science Outreach!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year, before the end of Winter Quarter, the City of San Diego hosts an event called the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lovestemsd.org/&#34;&gt;San Diego Festival of Science and Engineering&lt;/a&gt;—or SDFSE for short. At EXPO Day, organizations from nearby universities and local companies host booths for attendees to visit. In previous years, I participated in EXPO Day with the Biomedical Engineering Society (BMES) and Bioengineering Graduate Society (BEGS) at UCSD. This year, I helped staff a booth hosted by the Graduate Bioinformatics Council (GBIC) and the Undergraduate Bioinformatics Club (UBIC) at UCSD!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Currently at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/SDFSE?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#SDFSE&lt;/a&gt; for their annual Expo Day 2020! Teaching students about DNA using Legos and an Arduino sequencer 🙌🤩&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/phdlife?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#phdlife&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/AcademicTwitter?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#AcademicTwitter&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/compbio?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#compbio&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/59nOs5l1VW&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/59nOs5l1VW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michelle Franc Ragsac (@mragsac) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mragsac/status/1236421903935365121?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 7, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At our booth, we taught students basic concepts about the central dogma of biology, genetic inheritance, and genome sequencing—through some abstraction, of course. To do this, we prompted visitors to &amp;ldquo;build a monster&amp;rsquo;s DNA&amp;rdquo; with colored lego blocks. After stacking the blocks into the monster&amp;rsquo;s genome, we &amp;ldquo;sequenced&amp;rdquo; the DNA with our Arduino-built sequencing machine. Our machine had a laser that would translate each block&amp;rsquo;s color to a given nucleotide in a fashion similar to Illumina sequencing machines. With the monster&amp;rsquo;s DNA sequence, visitors could then determine their monster&amp;rsquo;s appearance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While EXPO day was exhausting to participate in, seeing people get excited about genomics and bioinformatics was super rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;13th-annual-genetics-training-program-retreat&#34;&gt;13th Annual Genetics Training Program Retreat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a part of the Genetics Training Program at UCSD, and each year, the 5th year class organizes an annual retreat for the program filled with research talks and poster presentations. While the poster presentations are mandatory, I was excited to piece together my project&amp;rsquo;s story for the first time in a scientific poster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Presented my poster at the UCSD 13th Annual Genetics Training Program Retreat 🙌 Cheers to the first poster of graduate school 💗 Next time, I&amp;#39;ll definitely include more pictures of Ciona ☺️ &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/RATwQxdwzA&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/RATwQxdwzA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michelle Franc Ragsac (@mragsac) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mragsac/status/1237496753907044352?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 10, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I presented on a project I worked on during my research rotation in &lt;a href=&#34;https://farleylab.com/&#34;&gt;Emma Farley&amp;rsquo;s laboratory&lt;/a&gt;—a project that convinced me to stay in the lab! In the lab, we&amp;rsquo;re interested in studying early development using the model organism &lt;em&gt;Ciona intestinalis&lt;/em&gt;. While previous studies have provided insight into how cells determine when and where they turn into different tissue types, we wanted to develop a better understanding of these processes. To do this, we used single-cell sequencing to figure out what genes are active in individual cells of a given tissue type during different time points of development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my project, I learned how to analyze the data using tools such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.10xgenomics.com/single-cell-gene-expression/software/pipelines/latest/what-is-cell-ranger&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cellranger&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;code&gt;UNIX&lt;/code&gt; command line and &lt;a href=&#34;https://satijalab.org/seurat/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Seurat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; programming language. Analyzing the data helped us discover genes that are specific to certain cell types but have a relatively unknown function in &lt;em&gt;Ciona&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited to finish up this project soon so that I can write it up to put on this website!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;covid-19-at-ucsd&#34;&gt;COVID-19 at UCSD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During an pneumonia outbreak investigation in Wuhan, China in late 2019, investigators discovered the emergence of a respiratory illness now known as coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). On &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2020/p0121-novel-coronavirus-travel-case.html&#34;&gt;January 21, 2020&lt;/a&gt;, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) reported the first positive case in the United States from a patient that had recently traveled to Washington state from Wuhan. Following this, UCSD Chancellor Pradeep Khosla sent out a notice on Valentine&amp;rsquo;s Day about the university&amp;rsquo;s dedication to safeguarding the health and wellness of its students, staff, and faculty. He also sent out a link to a website that would provide UCSD-specific updates about COVID-19: &lt;a href=&#34;https://coronavirus.ucsd.edu/&#34;&gt;https://coronavirus.ucsd.edu/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That happened during my &lt;a href=&#34;https://mragsac.github.io/2020/03/01/winter-quarter-2020-update-health-student-activism/&#34;&gt;last update&lt;/a&gt;. While thoughts about the virus were at the back of my mind, I didn&amp;rsquo;t pay much attention to them. Just in case anything needed to happen, my lab came up with a strategy for how we would all work from home if need be, but none of us felt as if a shutdown would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things then started changing very rapidly at UCSD from the administrative end:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On &lt;a href=&#34;http://adminrecords.ucsd.edu/Notices/2020/2020-3-11-1.html&#34;&gt;March 11, 2020&lt;/a&gt;, the university canceled all in-person, on-campus Winter Quarter 2020 final exams in favor of online final exams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On &lt;a href=&#34;http://adminrecords.ucsd.edu/Notices/2020/2020-3-13-3.html&#34;&gt;March 13, 2020&lt;/a&gt;, the university started encouraging non-essential personnel to work remotely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.ca.gov/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/3.19.20-attested-EO-N-33-20-COVID-19-HEALTH-ORDER.pdf&#34;&gt;March 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;, CA Governor Gavin Newsom placed a statewide &amp;ldquo;shelter in place&amp;rdquo; order&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On &lt;a href=&#34;http://adminrecords.ucsd.edu/Notices/2020/2020-3-26-2.html&#34;&gt;March 26, 2020&lt;/a&gt;, the university mandated that all research must move as much activity as possible to an online setting with minimal numbers of on-site personnel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On &lt;a href=&#34;http://adminrecords.ucsd.edu/Notices/2020/2020-3-28-1.html&#34;&gt;March 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;, a UCSD student tested positive for COVID-19&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On &lt;a href=&#34;http://adminrecords.ucsd.edu/Notices/2020/2020-3-16-2.html&#34;&gt;March 29, 2020&lt;/a&gt;, the university encouraged students to move out of on-campus housing to enforce social distancing measures, and mandated that Spring Quarter 2020 be fully online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently in my second week of Spring Quarter 2020, and it&amp;rsquo;s been a little unsettling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The university-wide transition to an online work environment hasn&amp;rsquo;t been the most transparent for graduate students. Some students were allowed to work from home with no questions asked. Unfortunately, other graduate students were required to work on-campus despite feeling unsafe outside of their homes. While I don&amp;rsquo;t have much faith in the university investigating how faculty and departments responded appropriately to COVID-19, I hope that something happens to improve the working conditions of students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working from home since March 13th due to personal choice, and while I&amp;rsquo;m accustomed to working remotely, it&amp;rsquo;s been difficult. As a bioinformatician, I rely on data hosted on some remote server, and crunching numbers is the norm. In a perfect world, I would work from 9:00 AM to 5:00 PM with the occasional break for a walk outside or internet browsing. In a regular world without COVID-19, I prefer to work from &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;—instead of home, I prefer to work from a coffee shop or library. Working remotely is less distracting, and I find that I&amp;rsquo;m more productive when I&amp;rsquo;m removed from campus but still reachable online or over the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this reality, I feel on edge, anxious, and fatigued. I read sentences over and over again, and I forget the correct syntax for coding more often than before. No matter how early I sleep, I never want to wake up in the morning. I&amp;rsquo;m trying my best to complete tasks each day and stay productive, but it&amp;rsquo;s harder than usual with all of the Zoom meetings. Luckily, I haven&amp;rsquo;t been the only one feeling like this, and that in of itself is comforting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, these feelings dissipate in the coming days and we all feel a little less stressed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay healthy everybody!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winter Quarter 2020 Update: Health &amp; Student Activism</title>
      <link>https://mragsac.github.io/2020/03/01/winter-quarter-2020-update-health-student-activism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 09:35:45 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mragsac.github.io/2020/03/01/winter-quarter-2020-update-health-student-activism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I meant to make a post on February 29th because it would have been cool to post on leap day. However, I never got around to it. Here are some updates from this past quarter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-engineers-walk-into-a-bar&#34;&gt;Two Engineers Walk Into a Bar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my Gordon Engineering Leadership class (ENG 211), we had to perform a &amp;ldquo;stretch goal&amp;rdquo; to exercise the leadership skills that we were building in the class. For this stretch goal, we had to participate in &amp;ldquo;Two Engineers Walk Into a Bar.&amp;rdquo; The setup for this assignment was simple: take two—or in my group&amp;rsquo;s case, three—engineers, send them to a bar or other public place, and make them hold a sign that says, &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re Engineers! Ask us a question!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;



  











&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://mragsac.github.io/img/20200130_soda-and-swine.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Ross Turner, Alyssa Chiang, and me at UCSD Soda &amp;amp; Swine for Two Engineers Walk Into a Bar&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mragsac.github.io/img/20200130_soda-and-swine.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Ross Turner, Alyssa Chiang, and me at UCSD Soda &amp;amp; Swine for Two Engineers Walk Into a Bar
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To complete this stretch assignment, my group went to UCSD&amp;rsquo;s new on-campus &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yelp.com/biz/soda-and-swine-ucsd-la-jolla&#34;&gt;Soda &amp;amp; Swine restaurant&lt;/a&gt; for their Thursday afternoon Happy Hour! Even though the food was a little pricey, it was nice to be able to talk with my group mates about graduate school and the learning environment at UCSD. Unfortunately, we weren&amp;rsquo;t able to convince people to visit our table, but the assignment was still a whole lot of fun! Next time, I would try &amp;ldquo;Two Engineers Walk Into a Bar&amp;rdquo; somewhere off-campus to engage more with the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brief-summary-of-february&#34;&gt;A Brief Summary of February&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February was quite a busy month for me and my graduate program as a whole. Here&amp;rsquo;s the low down of the events that happened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I applied and was selected to become an instructor for my program&amp;rsquo;s Welcome Week Bootcamp for incoming students. The Welcome Week Bootcamp is a week-long course for incoming Bioinformatics &amp;amp; Systems Biology graduate students meant to introduce you to the program faculty and the resources needed to succeed in your first-year research rotations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My graduate program had its Recruitment Weekend, and it was jam-packed with activities meant to convince interview candidates to come to our school. There&amp;rsquo;s welcome dinners, interviews, lunches, presentations, and lots of networking!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Steering Committee for my graduate program had its quarterly meeting in February. The Steering Committee decides the strategic plan for my graduate program, and they&amp;rsquo;re in charge of the curriculum, admissions, stipend, and more. They requested an update on student activities, so some other students and I compiled a report on graduate student accomplishments and solicited grievances that students wanted to bring up to the faculty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I went on a field trip to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epsilonsystems.com/&#34;&gt;Epsilon Systems Solutions&lt;/a&gt; with the Gordon Center as part of my engineering leadership class. During this field trip, I was able to gather valuable insight into the recruitment process and what employers look for out of a prospective engineering applicant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several friends from the Bay Area came to visit me in San Diego! We visited various breweries and restaurants during their stay—however, a brief volleyball game re-aggravated my sciatica. I was left debilitated for a week! While things are better now, I&amp;rsquo;m still having some difficulty walking or exercising as much as I used to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these events, combined with research and teaching, made it very difficult to prioritize what needed to get done versus what could sit on the back burner. It felt like my goals of completing my research project were slipping through my fingers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;departmental-pressures-and-the-resulting-student-fatigue&#34;&gt;Departmental Pressures and the Resulting Student Fatigue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past month, I felt a lot of pressure from the systematic structures of my graduate program. For the recruitment weekend, students and administration were the key players in organizing events, coordinating travel across the large UCSD campus, and managing several of the weekend&amp;rsquo;s expenses! Whenever an interview candidate complimented the breadth of student involvement, I felt my shoulders feel more weighed down by the lack of faculty support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, preparing for the Steering Committee meeting was especially stressful. For my graduate program, we host a Town Hall meeting once a year as a forum for students to provide input to the Program Chairs on the current student environment. At the last Town Hall meeting during Spring 2019, the current Program Chair at the time was only present for 30 minutes! To garner more program awareness of student issues, several students and I gathered current student input to present at the Steering Committee meeting through a survey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it was comforting to see that students generally shared the same sentiment towards the program faculty versus program administration, most students felt defeated as a whole. Most students were not confident in the department&amp;rsquo;s ability to act on their promises to improve the coursework, raise the stipend, or even care about student life in Bioinformatics &amp;amp; Systems Biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading these responses, combined with participating in the recruitment weekend, made me feel hopeless about the state of faculty disinterest in the structure of our program and student input. As a highly-involved student activist in a program that is seemingly resistant to change, this whole situation made February one of the worst months in the academic year to date. Sometimes, I wonder what would happen if I left these calls for policy changes to other students. When I think about that, combined with the fact that there are only about five other students that would put their research aside for student advocacy, I feel overwhelmed. As of late, I feel a little better, yet still pressured by this imposing need to convince faculty to show their support for their students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wise person once told me something with the gist of, &amp;ldquo;While you may have the best intentions, it&amp;rsquo;s the way your actions are perceived that leave the overall impact.&amp;rdquo; Nowadays, I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about this phrase &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; when it comes to departmental drama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been finishing up a large, important portion of my research that I hope to share on this blog soon! In the meantime, look out for another update in the coming week or so. I&amp;rsquo;ll be presenting a project that I had in the Farley Lab at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://genetics.ucsd.edu/annual-retreat/index.html&#34;&gt;13th Annual UCSD Genetics Training Program Retreat&lt;/a&gt;. I just finished the poster earlier today and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting Winter Quarter 2020</title>
      <link>https://mragsac.github.io/2020/01/26/starting-winter-quarter-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 15:08:58 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mragsac.github.io/2020/01/26/starting-winter-quarter-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So far, this quarter has been a whirlwind! I&amp;rsquo;ve been focusing a lot more on my research project, but some of my other responsibilities just take up more time than I anticipated so I don&amp;rsquo;t actually end up getting as much done as I would like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;coursework-recap&#34;&gt;Coursework Recap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very close to finishing the course requirements for &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinformatics.ucsd.edu/&#34;&gt;my graduate program&lt;/a&gt;! This quarter, I decided to decrease my course load in order to focus a bit more on research and other duties. I&amp;rsquo;ll be finishing up my course electives next Spring Quarter 2020!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Winter Quarter 2020, I&amp;rsquo;m taking the following classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BIOM 242: Seminar in Genetics&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;As part of the UCSD Genetics Training Program, I&amp;rsquo;m required to participate in this weekly journal club in which students present and discuss papers on the principles of classical and molecular genetics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BNFO 281. Seminar in Bioinformatics &amp;amp; Systems Biology&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; My program, in partnership with the UCSD Genetics Training Program, has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomic.weebly.com/&#34;&gt;weekly seminar series&lt;/a&gt; where invited faculty members from various universities give presentations on their research. While the talks are more genomics and genetics focused, they&amp;rsquo;re generally quite good even though people in my program are required to attend for the first two years of graduate study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BNFO 283. Bioinformatics Student Research Talks&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;For my program, we have a weekly seminar course where 1st- and 2nd-Year graduate students practice their presentation skills by giving a talk in front their peers and interested faculty members. This quarter, since I&amp;rsquo;m a 2nd Year student, we&amp;rsquo;re supposed to be presenting draft versions of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinformatics.ucsd.edu/node/37&#34;&gt;Qualifying Examination&lt;/a&gt; talk!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENG 211. Engineering Leadership in Academia&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;This quarter, I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to just focus entirely on research, so I tried looking for classes that weren&amp;rsquo;t necessarily &amp;ldquo;academic&amp;rdquo;, but classes that could offer some practical skills for during and after graduate school. I was able to find a class taught by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://jacobsschool.ucsd.edu/GordonCenter/&#34;&gt;Gordon Engineering Leadership Center&lt;/a&gt; at UCSD that focuses on teaching engineering leadership with fun and interactive exercises!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;organizational-structures-and-leadership-with-the-gordon-center&#34;&gt;Organizational Structures and Leadership with the Gordon Center&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the most exciting class this quarter is definitely ENG 211! So far, my favorite experience from the class was an interactive activity on &lt;em&gt;organizational structures&lt;/em&gt; that we had two weeks ago. In this activity, our class (of around 20 students or so) was split into a total of five groups: one &amp;ldquo;Top&amp;rdquo; group, two &amp;ldquo;Middle&amp;rdquo; groups, and two &amp;ldquo;Bottom&amp;rdquo; groups upon entering the classroom. When the whole class had settled down into their groups, we found out the scenario of the activity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all members of a bridge building engineering company. Everybody in the &amp;ldquo;Bottom&amp;rdquo; group is a part of the engineering team within the company. Everybody in the &amp;ldquo;Middle&amp;rdquo; group is a member of middle management within the company, which manages the &amp;ldquo;Bottom&amp;rdquo; people. Finally, everybody in the &amp;ldquo;Top&amp;rdquo; group is a member of the executive board within the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this activity, a customer has come to the company and has commissioned designs for a bridge that can cross over a riverbank within the city. The goal of this activity is to produce designs for this client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this activity, I was a part of the &amp;ldquo;Bottom&amp;rdquo; group; there were ten of us total. For the &amp;ldquo;Middle&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Top&amp;rdquo; groups, there were four and three people in each of those groups, respectively. While this activity seemed pretty simple at first, more details were given to us about the scenario:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To increase morale within the company, it was decided that this client&amp;rsquo;s request be turned into an internal competition. There will be two &amp;ldquo;Bottom&amp;rdquo; groups, and each bottom group is to be managed by their own group of &amp;ldquo;Middle&amp;rdquo; managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, each &amp;ldquo;Middle&amp;rdquo; management team was given a piece of paper with the client specifications for the bridge, along with building supplies (e.g. wood barrel #2 pencils, paper clips, green card stock, and printer paper) that were each associated with their own cost. The goal of the activity was to build a small toll bridge that could be built efficiently according to the parameters provided, and that could sustain the weight of 20 cars (represented by metal bolts) while earning a profit over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, information about what the client wanted weren&amp;rsquo;t given directly to the &amp;ldquo;Bottom&amp;rdquo; teams! That information was given to our &amp;ldquo;Middle&amp;rdquo; managers from the client, and we had to rely on an elaborate game of telephone to communicate what materials we needed to build the bridge, what progress we&amp;rsquo;ve made on the project to &amp;ldquo;Top&amp;rdquo; management, and other things! It was a fun, highly-interactive activity that showed the complexities of information flow within an organization, as well as the politics within corporations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I&amp;rsquo;ll be completing one of the assignments for the class dubbed as a &amp;ldquo;Stretch Goal&amp;rdquo;. For this assignment, I&amp;rsquo;ll be sitting down at a bar with two other students holding a sign that says, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m an Engineer! Ask Me Questions!&amp;quot;. While I&amp;rsquo;m nervous about putting myself out there, I&amp;rsquo;m excited to see what questions people ask or if people even come up to us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;teaching-practical-bioinformatics-101&#34;&gt;Teaching Practical Bioinformatics 101&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to taking classes, I&amp;rsquo;m also helping Prof. Alon Goren teach a course in &amp;ldquo;Quantitative Methods in Genetics and Genomics&amp;rdquo; (listed as CMM 262) as one of three Graduate Teaching Assistants. Technically, I&amp;rsquo;m supposed to be taking this course as a part of the Genetics Training Program requirements, but hopefully, &lt;em&gt;teaching it&lt;/em&gt; counts towards the requirement!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the course description from our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/biom262/cmm262-2020&#34;&gt;GitHub website&lt;/a&gt; in case you&amp;rsquo;re interested:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quantitative Methods in Genetics and Genomics is designed to teach experimental and analytical approaches in modern genetics and genomics, from experimental design through data analysis in each of several topic areas. Lecturers this year include Daniela Nachmanson, Scott Rifkin, Robert Morey, Olivier Harismendy, Alon Goren, Graham McVicker, Ondrej Libiger, Nicholas Schork, Hannah Carter, Pablo Tamayo, and William Kim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helping TA the class has been a great refresher into the different bioinformatics tools that people use for RNA-sequencing analysis and other pipelines! The class itself is highly interactive, and each week focuses on a different genomics analysis toolkit to teach students about through hands-on programming exercises in &lt;a href=&#34;https://jupyter.org/&#34;&gt;Jupyter Notebooks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/lesson-10.html&#34;&gt;R Markdown Notebooks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we move into Week 4 of the academic quarter, I hope that I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to make some decent progress on my research so that I can post about it here! I&amp;rsquo;m also working on a new section of this website that&amp;rsquo;ll feature tools that I use to stay organized, productive, and even not so productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall Quarter 2019 and Winter Vacation Recap</title>
      <link>https://mragsac.github.io/2020/01/09/fall-quarter-2019-and-winter-vacation-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 13:18:51 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mragsac.github.io/2020/01/09/fall-quarter-2019-and-winter-vacation-recap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fall Quarter 2019 passed by very quickly since the last time I was updating this website, and then I got so caught up in my holiday vacation that I forgot to update things! My goal is to blog semi-regularly, so let&amp;rsquo;s hope that happens—fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;coursework-recap&#34;&gt;Coursework Recap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinformatics.ucsd.edu/&#34;&gt;my graduate program&lt;/a&gt;, students generally take courses during their first two years of study. Because I’m a part of the &amp;ldquo;Bioinformatics &amp;amp; Systems Biology&amp;rdquo; (BISB) track, I spent last year—my first year—taking core courses in bioinformatics algorithms, genomics and proteomics, statistics, and network biology. In addition to these core courses, my program requires that I take several elective courses in topics of my choosing. However, we&amp;rsquo;re required to take at least one computer science class (e.g. algorithms, machine learning, data mining, or modeling) and at least one biology class (e.g. biochemistry, molecular genetics, or cell biology). During Fall Quarter 2019, I took two elective courses to try and satisfy these requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CSE 258. Recommender Systems and Web Mining&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;to fulfill my computer science elctive, as well as get an overview of machine learning techniques &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;[Course Website: http://cseweb.ucsd.edu/classes/fa19/cse258-a/]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MED 268. Statistics Concepts for Biomedical Research&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;to fulfill a general elective requirement, and review some concepts in statistics and how those concepts can be applied to biomedical experiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was nervous to take these classes, I would highly recommend them to students in Bioinformatics, Biomedical Informatics, Biomedical Sciences, or even Biology! For CSE 258, the course was taught from a practical standpoint, and focused on the exact packages that people would use to input their own data into machine learning models. Additionally, MED 268 was the best statistics course that I have ever taken! It was taught using the R programming language and focused on easing people (mainly medical students and biologists without any programming experience) into using existing packages to perform power analyses, plotting, and other evaluations of their data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite having homework assignments nearly every week, I thought taking these two courses were worth it, and I feel like I left Fall Quarter having learned a good amount of practical skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;winter-vacation&#34;&gt;Winter Vacation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the quarter, I was starting to feel a little fatigued. Honestly, I wasn’t really enjoying the project that I was working on, and it felt like I kept getting sucked into hours of debugging my code. I felt like I was drowning in assignments: working on my final project for CSE, studying for my MED final exam, and finishing up milestones for my research project! When the quarter ended, and I finished my meetings on my last day at school before the holiday, it felt like a massive weight had been lifted off my shoulders. I was also finally able to deep clean my apartment!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the winter holiday, I flew back to San Francisco to visit family for Christmas and New Year&amp;rsquo;s celebrations. During my time at home, it was nice to get updated on the latest family gossip, as well as spend time making and eating my favorite foods that I grew up with. As I watched the entirety of Star Wars theatrical releases over the span of two days and slept in until 9:30AM on Weekday mornings, I felt myself recharging after the hustle and bustle of the academic quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in every conversation I had with family, there were always the looming questions of, &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s taking so long in school?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Are you going to be a real doctor?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Why haven&amp;rsquo;t you finished yet?&amp;rdquo; or even &amp;ldquo;Why aren&amp;rsquo;t you working yet?&amp;quot;. As one of the first in my first-generation family to pursue graduate education—let alone undergraduate education in the United States—it was exhausting to continuously explain and re-explain the system or tell them what I was doing in school and why I was still in school. I felt myself resorting to responses like, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll be done soon, don&amp;rsquo;t worry&amp;rdquo;, to ease their concerns over my future self&amp;rsquo;s ability to find a job, have kids, or get married.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I enjoyed going home for the holidays, but it reminded me of how much &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; I should visit home to stay in touch. The vacation also reminded me of the importance of taking breaks and building in time into my schedule to decompress during the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&amp;rsquo;m finally back in San Diego and completely set-up for Winter Quarter 2020! I&amp;rsquo;ll give an update on how things are going later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
